The Substitute 2: School's Out is a action, mystery,
thriller film directed by Steven Pearl.
When teacher Randall Thomasson is killed during a carjacking, an unexpected visitor
shows up at his funeral - his estranged brother, Karl Thomasson.
An ex-Green Beret turned mercenary, Karl signs on as a new
substitute teacher in order to investigate Randall's murder.
Karl Thomasson, played by Treat Williams.
Warren Drummond, played by BD Wong.
Joey 6, played by Angel David.
Kara Lavelle, played by Michael Michele.
Dontae, played by Lawrence Gilliard Jr..
Anya Thomasson, played by Susan May Pratt.
The Substitute 2: School's Out is a 1998 straight-to-DVD action-crime-thriller film directed by Steven Pearl and starring Treat Williams as Carl Thomasson (later spelled
Karl in the sequels), a mercenary who masquerades as a teacher in order to enter a tough urban school and wreak his revenge upon his brother's killer.
The film has very little connection to The Substitute, other than Joey Six (protagonist Jonathan Shale's only surviving mercenary in the
first film, this time portrayed by Angel David instead of Raymond Cruz) aiding Thomasson during the course of the movie.
A reference early in the film indicates, through a photograph and short conversation between Thomasson and Joey Six, that Shale
and Jane Hetzko (Shale's girlfriend) had married and now teach in foreign nations as part of the Peace Corps.
It is also noted that Shale and Thomasson had served in the
Army, as well as worked as mercenaries together.
The film explores themes of high school, teacher, gang.
The tone is intense and lighthearted and mind_bending.